hey folks David to with Barb ben.com and
today we're recapping some of the
highlights from the 2023 weightlifting
World Championships they were held in
Saudi Arabia this year and it was the
last World Championships before the 2024
Paris Olympics a lot is at stake there
were some great world record
performances we're going to recap just
some of the highlights there were too
many great sessions and frankly too many
great lists to fit in one video so these
were just some of our favorites before
we get into that make sure to subscribe
to barbend on YouTube to stay up toate
on all things strength some quick
context there was a lot at stake for
this year's World Championships it was
an important qualifier event for the
2024 Paris Olympics which by the way
could be the last Olympic Games we see
weightlifting in for a while
weightlifting position in the Olympic
program is not guaranteed Beyond Paris
so this one felt like it had some extra
pressure attached to it let's start with
maybe the most competitive session and
it was the first one to kick off the
women's 49 kg weight category and it was
really about battle between two lifters
from China now because of qualification
rules they can only send one lifter to
the Paris Olympics in this weight
category and so it really came down to
the wire in a battle between 2020
Olympic champion ho and 2022 World
Champion Jang Jang came out just ahead
they tied in the snatch but Jang pulled
ahead in the cleaning jerk and ended up
setting a world record total putting
herself in Prime position for Paris
qualification also of note the United
States Jordan Dela Cruz medaled for the
first time in her fourth world
championship appearance she earned
Bronze in the cleaning jerk and total in
the men 61 kgam category it was actually
the story of a lifter who didn't total
that makes our highlight recap Hampton
Morris of the United States still a
junior lifter bombed out in the snatch
but made 168 Kg on his final clean and
jerk attempt to set a junior world
record and also to secure a gold medal
in The kleaning Jerk he becomes the
first American male to secure a gold
medal at the world championships in
nearly four decades and by the way he
had to out clean and jerk the defending
Olympic champion to do so so Hampton
Morris definitely one to watch out for
heading into Paris we already knew that
but he's out here out clean and jerking
Olympic gold medalists could he make a
run at the podium in Paris I think he's
got a real shot if he can put together a
consistent day on the snatch let's move
to the men's 73 kgam category and out of
all of the sessions in Saudi Arabia
this was the most interesting because
the winner in the total the overall
world champion came from the C group
we've seen people win from the B group
but the C group that is a new one
Thailand's wuma WEA phone came out of
nowhere recorded a 349 kg total
including a 195 kg cleaning jerk and he
won the overall gold medal out of the
cgroup no one from the B group or a
group could catch him a remarkable
performance that kind of came out of
nowhere and really left the audience
stunned we're still getting over it I
mean a fantastic performance from the
lifter from Thailand and I guess now
someone to watch for metal contention at
Future international events oh and by
the way he's still a junior and that 195
kgam cleaning jerk was a junior world
record the men's 89 kilogram category
was set to be one of the most
competitive during this year's World
Championships at least when it came to
athletes from different countries I'm
going to list who we were keeping our
eyes on for potential gold medal
performances I'm going to read it off
here Carlos Nasser Antonino pizolato TN
we've heard that name before Lee dinin
Kar Valena Sanchez and Arley Mendes
six-way Collision Course for Glory in
the men's 89 kgam category so who won
absolutely none of them Naser too
injured to compete pisol lat bombed out
in the snatch Tien bombed out in the
cleaning jerk denen tore his hand open
and had an underwhelming performance and
Mendes just wasn't anywhere to be found
like he didn't show up Den finished in
silver medal overall with that torn hand
and that gave Iran's Mir Mustafa javadi
a one in a million shot as barbin riter
Jake Dixon says to secure his gold medal
and he won by a single kilogram and to
do that he had to clean a jerk a
whopping 10 kilos over anything we've
ever seen him hit on the iwf
international stage it was truly a Max
effort lift and he was rewarded with an
overall gold medal for that Herculean
effort China's Leu huano broke through
in the men's 102 kilogram category he
moved up in the past year and a half
from 89 kilos and came away with gold
overall it's an impactful performance
from him and it also establishes China's
dominance in yet another men's weight
class let's talk about the women's super
heavyweight category the weight category
over 87 kg by the time the snatches were
done before a single clean and jerk had
been attempted in the a session three of
the top ranked four women in the world
had either bombed out or withdrawn
including defending Olympic champion
that includes defending Olympic champion
Lee winwin Kus he Jang Park ended up
winning with a 289 kg total massive
Improvement on her eighth place finish
at last year's World Championships Mary
Tyson lapen of the United States who is
definitely a contender to make next
year's Olympic squad for America
finished in silver overall in her first
ever World Championships she's actually
been on our podcast before we had a
great time talking to her you should
definitely check that one out another
moment well in the men's super
heavyweight group lha talakad wins his
seventh World Championship overall
further cementing him as probably the
greatest super heavy weight of all time
and perhaps the greatest weightlifter of
all time he's been at the top of the
weight category since 2015 and it's been
tough for anyone to come within spitting
distance of his totals another lift that
wasn't ultimately reflected in the total
standings but I wanted to point out in
the men's super heavyweight category
armenia's Simone Marian who were used to
seeing win big in lower weight classes
well he's moved up to Super heavyweight
and he made a 250 kg cleaning jerk
becoming one of the lightest lifters in
history to ever hit that Mark he was
more than 47 kg lighter than Lasha
talakad the ultimate winner in the clean
and jerk and total for the event so
Simone Marian he has his work cut out to
qualify for the Olympics as a super
heavyweight out of Armenia but having
moved up in the weight class he's
clearly put on strength and clean and
jerking 250 kg at that light a body
weight a a historic feat and one that I
wanted to give a special shout out to
well we want to know what were your
favorite moments from the 2023 World
Championships in Saudi Arabia let us
know in the comments below we only
touched on a small smattering of some
great moments here thanks so much folks
hope you
[Music]
enjoyed